okay i'm going to try something a little
different today i just want to share
with you some of my reflections on
something I've been thinking about in
the last couple of days so I've been
rereading this awesome book right here
where mathematics comes from by Rafael
Nunez and George leg off it's a great
book because it introduces cognitive
science to the study of mathematical
thought and I've read this book before
but as I was reading it this weekend is
reflecting on the importance of bridging
the gap between three areas specific
knowledge bases like mathematics or
physics or chemistry or what have you
the field of cognitive science which is
looking at Lord's go BR look netam human
behavior in the mind and then the realm
of philosophy just the assumptions we
have about how things work and about
what is knowable and what is real and
what's good and what's bad and so on and
um I've been reading this book again
I've realized that one of the more
important things that cognitive science
can bring to other disciplines is what
George Lake often Mark Johnson call
empirically responsible philosophy now
empirically responsible philosophy is
simply recognizing that our assumptions
about philosophical topics can be skewed
or biased by our worldviews and by our
value systems and so we can actually
have blind spots very significant blind
spots about the world and so it's
possible to develop for very elaborate
philosophical arguments that are really
untrue in a very foundational level make
an assumption about the human mind that
has been validated by research in brain
science for example and what's needed to
remedy this problem when it arises is to
have a really strong understanding of
what cognitive science is telling us
about human nature and about the mind
about language and thought so that when
we articulate a philosophical argument
we can determine whether or not it's
empirically responsible are we being
responsible with our understanding
of where our philosophies come from
whether or not they're correct and if
we're making assumptions about human
beings that fly in the face of what
science has told us about what it means
to be human now I think this is
something that's especially important
when you look at the application of
philosophy to economics where we have
different theories about rational action
and economic behavior and the theories
are basically ad hoc assumptions have no
basis in reality they were formulated
oftentimes by mathematicians or by
people who don't know much of anything
about real human behavior and so the
theories can stand for decades in some
cases without ever being tested relative
to what is known and psychology and
brain research in anthropological
research and in other fields that could
guide us more effectively so when we
need to solve big problems like building
a sustainable global economy we don't
want to just have philosophies that are
ad hoc we want to have ways as
systematically determining whether what
we're doing is in the right ballpark
course we're completely off our rocker
it turns out cognitive science can help
us to do that so I've been advocating
for a number of years now that cognitive
science should be taught and should be
employed as part of our work in
developing philosophies for a society
and for building our social policies so
that we can be more effective at solving
real-world problems I'd love to know
what you think about this